<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Remarks of an university-man upon a late book, falsly called A vindication of the primitive fathers, against the imputations of Gilbert Lord Bishop of Sarum, written by Mr. Hill of Killmington</title>
            <author>Willes, John, 1646 or 7-1700.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 91 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66115</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2302</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11250</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12929490</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12929490</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95617</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66115)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95617)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 991:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Remarks of an university-man upon a late book, falsly called A vindication of the primitive fathers, against the imputations of Gilbert Lord Bishop of Sarum, written by Mr. Hill of Killmington</title>
                  <author>Willes, John, 1646 or 7-1700.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Ri. Chiswell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to John Willes. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Burnet, Gilbert, 1643-1715.</term>
               <term>Hill, Samuel, 1648-1716. --  Vindication of the primitive fathers against the imputations of Gilbert Lord Bishop of Sarum.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Doctrines.</term>
               <term>Apologetics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Apologetics --  History --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95617:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95617:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>REMARKS Of an Univerſity-Man UPON A Late BOOK, Falſly called <hi>A Vindication of the Primitive Fathers, againſt the Imputations of</hi> Gilbert <hi>Lord Biſhop of</hi> Sarum. <hi>Written by Mr.</hi> Hill <hi>of</hi> Killmington.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Ri. Chiſwell,</hi> at the <hi>Roſe and Crown</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. MDCXCV.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:95617:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:95617:2"/>
            <head>REMARKS UPON A late Book, falſly called <hi>A Vindication of the Primitive Fathers,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THE great Satisfaction I had in reading <hi>the Lord Biſhop of</hi> Sarum'<hi>s Four Diſcourſes to his Clergy,</hi> and that eſpecially, concerning <hi>the Divinity of our Saviour,</hi> (wherein I met with ſuch excellent Arguments, as I had not found in other Authors, for the Confirmation of that great <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of our Faith,</hi>) oblig'd me to think that they could not but be receiv'd with as general an Eſteem and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, as, in my Judgment, they deſerv'd. And as I was perſuaded they would be extreamly uſeful, ſo I could not but imagine they would remain unexcepted againſt, by the moſt Malicious and Ill-natured, unleſs they were ſuch as denied the very <hi>Divinity of our Saviour.</hi> All which, I was the more fully convinc'd of, and believ'd I might relie upon them, as agreeable to the true and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Doctrine of the Church, ſince they appeared in Publick with the Approbation and <hi>Licence</hi> of the never enough to be admired Late <hi>Archbiſhop of</hi> Canterbury, whoſe Sincerity, Clearneſs, and Strength of Judgment, I was well aſſured, would approve of nothing as the Doctrine of the <hi>Church,</hi> and fit to believed by its <hi>Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy,</hi> which deſerv'd the <hi>Cenſure of a Convocation.</hi> And though there came out ſome Exceptions againſt the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Diſcourſe,</hi> which relates to <hi>the Divinity and Death
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:95617:3"/> of Chriſt,</hi> as well as againſt <hi>the Archbiſhop's Sermons,</hi> and <hi>one of the Biſhop of</hi> Worceſter'<hi>s,</hi> by the <hi>Socinian</hi> Party; yet they appear'd ſo trifling, (eſpecially ſince they have been anſwered <hi>by the Biſhop of</hi> Sarum'<hi>s Letter to Dr.</hi> Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liams, which is annex'd to his <hi>Learned Vindication of the other Two</hi>) that they rather confirm'd than leſſen'd my Opinion of it. But I muſt confeſs, I was ſomething ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pris'd, and began to diſtruſt my Judgment, when I ſaw Mr. <hi>Hill's Book</hi> come forth with ſuch a Title, as I thought was almoſt enough, had there<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> been nothing more in it, to have made <hi>the Biſhop's Second<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Diſcourſe,</hi> which is the only one aim'd at, be cenſur'd as Heretical; and, had it been made good, muſt have thought it my Duty alſo, as being a Member of one of thoſe Bodies, to <hi>whoſe Judgment</hi> the Book is referred, as well as to the <hi>Church <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal,</hi> the <hi>Archbiſhops and Biſhops of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>and the next Seſſion of Convocation,</hi> to aſſiſt at the Solemnity of condemning the Biſhop himſelf for an Heretick. But when I conſidered that it was grown to too general a Cuſtom, for Authors to make large and ſpecious Titles, to make amends for the emptineſs of the Book; and that they oftner give a <hi>Specimen</hi> of their own ill Nature, than of any real <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors they diſcover;</hi> I began to be no more concern'd at the Title, than I was at the mighty Quotations which this Author makes uſe of; when I conſidered, that by turning to the <hi>Indexes</hi> of the <hi>Paris Editions of the Fathers in our Publick Library,</hi> I could quote as much, and as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to the Purpoſe as our <hi>Author has done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am almoſt apt to think, it would be labour loſt to run through his whole Book, to detect every Abſurdity in it; ſince I believe thoſe who have read the Preface to it, were ſo ſufficiently convinc'd of the weakneſs of the Author, that they could not think it worth their while to make any farther ſearch into it. 'Tis a great deal of Pity that the Letter, which he mentions to have ſent to his Lordſhip, did not appear with the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face; for certainly it muſt have prov'd as great a Satire upon himſelf, as the Preface appears to be. But I am
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:95617:3"/> too forward in my Cenſure; for, if you will believe him, the Biſhop is mightily beholding to him for his gentle uſage of him, and for not divulging ſome <hi>Private Practice;</hi> which upon fitting terms he is contented to <hi>huſh up at preſent.</hi> And therefore his Lordſhip had not beſt provoke him, and think of returning an Anſwer; for if he doth, he ſhall then be ſet free from all Obligations to Secrecy and good Manners; and then Wo betide him. This I take to be the Senſe of what follows, <hi>viz. But for the Private Practice objected to him, I will at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſpare him; and if his Lordſhip will be ſo kind to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the Matter ſhall be huſhed up.</hi> A trifling and Childiſh Inſinuation: For had the Biſhop been really guilty of any ſuch <hi>Private Practice,</hi> as would have been a diſhonourable Reflection upon him. I queſtion not, but we ſhould have heard more of it; ſince ſo much Malice could never have let ſlip ſo fair an Occaſion, without making the beſt Improvements of it, had there been any thing more, that could have advanc'd the Credit of the other Aſperſions, or have been any ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port to the weakneſs of the Cauſe. The reſt of the Preface is of the ſame Piece; and thus he concludes it; <hi>But as to his Doctrine, it is gone abroad, and cannot return; and if it be of evil Influence on young Students, or Men prepar'd to Irreligion, or of diſhonourable Reflection to the preſent Reign, or State of Religion; every Man has a juſt right, fairly and bravely to oppoſe it, without fear of Men, or reſpect of Perſons: And if it be not ſo, I promiſe his Lordſhip the moſt publick Recantation and Penance.</hi> And, ſuppoſing he ſhould be oblig'd to undergo it, with the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſeverity the Law could inflict, he may remain a laſting and ſad Example, of the Puniſhment due to all Libellers, and to all malicious Forgers of Falſehood. For though I have made a very diligent ſearch into the Biſhop's Diſcourſe, and into the Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons this Author has made againſt it; yet I do ſolemnly proteſt, that I do not find any one of thoſe Charges made good againſt it. What he means by theſe Words of <hi>diſhonourable Reflection to the preſent Reign,</hi> I can't
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:95617:4"/> gueſs; I believe they are not only very rude, but ſuch a malicious Inſinuation, as if it can be underſtood, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves a more ſevere Anſwer, and of a different Nature, than I am able to give him. <hi>How fairly and bravely he has oppoſed</hi> any thing that the Biſhop has ſaid, or rather, how fairly and openly he has rendred himſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible, is now high time to conſider.</p>
            <p>He begins his Book with a great deal of Confidence, and ſupercilious Contempt; <hi>That he has Two things to urge againſt the Lord Biſhop of</hi> Sarum, <hi>in his Diſcourſe on the Divinity and Death of Chriſt. 1. That the Biſhop ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry defectively (to ſay no worſe) ſtates our Faith and Doctrine in the Articles of the Trinity and Incarnation. And 2. That he expoſes the Fathers under the ſame, and worſe Imputations; which is the Second thing, that,</hi> he ſays, <hi>offends.</hi> All that the Biſhop ſays of the Fathers, if I miſtake him not, is to this purpoſe; That though the <hi>Fathers</hi> might have the ſame Notions of the Trinity, that we now have, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>That every one of the Bleſſed Three has a peculiar Diſtinction in himſelf, by which he is truly Different from the other Two;</hi> yet in their Explanations of this Doctrine, they often went ſo far, as might give occaſion to ſome to think, <hi>that they believ'd an Inequality between the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and a Subordination of the Second and Third to the Firſt.</hi> And their Explanatory Notions of the Trinity ſeem ſometimes to carry them beyond thoſe Bounds the Holy Scriptures had ſet them. By all which, his Lordſhip could deſign nothing more, than to ſhew us, That ſince ſome, even of the Fathers, were ſometimes confounded in their Explanations of that Sacred Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivable Myſtery, it would be great Preſumption in us to offer to explain the Modes, or to pretend to have any adequate Conceptions of it. That we may not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to dive into the Depths of thoſe Myſteries, which the Primitive Ages of the Church could never Fathom. And if they unhappily failed in the Attempt, it will be great Arrogance in us to hope of having any better Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs. Nor do I find the leaſt Shadow of Reaſon, to think<note place="margin">Pag. 2.</note> that the Biſhop in any part of his Diſcourſe, as our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:95617:4"/> too falſly and maliciouſly inſinuates, <hi>cenſures the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick and Eſtabliſht Principles of the Ancients;</hi> but only ſhews us ſome of their Failures and Imperfections. He denies not, that the Fathers believ'd a Trinity, as the Scriptures had revealed it; but only, that they were at a loſs, when they offer'd to make the manner of it intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligible, which is <hi>to take away the Myſteriouſneſs of it.</hi> And I wonder how our Author has the Confidence to ſay more.</p>
            <p>I will give this parallel Inſtance, which may ſerve both to defend and illuſtrate what the Biſhop has ſaid upon this Subject of the Fathers, which our pretended <hi>Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator,</hi> where there is the leaſt neceſſity for it, makes the greateſt noiſe about. We of the <hi>Church of</hi> England, do certainly believe, and can undeniably prove, that the Primitive Church were of the ſame Doctrine and Faith with us, concerning the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> that there was no Corporal, but only a Sacramental Preſence of Chriſt's Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; yet we alſo confeſs, that ſome of the Fathers have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt themſelves in ſome of their Writings, in ſuch high Strains, and Figurative Raptures, as might give occaſion to ſome to think, that they meant a Corporal Preſence by thoſe lofty Expreſſions, which only their height of Devotion drew from them. After the ſame manner, we may conclude, that though the Fathers believed the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Trinity, as it is revealed in Scripture, yet in their Explanations of the Modes and Manner of it, ſome of them may have given us Cauſe to think, that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of thoſe Expreſſions which they have let fall about it, as well as of the forementioned Doctrine, went far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than they were inſtructed or warranted by God's Word. And this I think may be ſufficient to explain the Biſhop's Senſe about the Fathers, if I underſtand him aright, and to anſwer all thoſe ill Natur'd Exceptions, which our Vindicator has very unjuſtly fram'd againſt it. But I ſhall have more to ſay to him in his due place.</p>
            <p>I ſhall then examine his firſt Charge againſt the Biſhop,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>viz. That he foully ſtates the Faith of the Divinity and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:95617:5"/> Incarnation of Chriſt, and therein of the Holy Trinity.</hi> Of which, ſays our Author, <hi>The Biſhop tells us, there have been three Opinions; the Socinian, Arian, and that which he would have called the Catholick and Chriſtian Faith.</hi> Now where is the Fault of all this? and yet, as I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, this is one of the Chiefeſt <hi>Imputations of Hereſie</hi> againſt the Biſhop. I never heard any Man yet ſo much as ſpoken againſt, for ſaying that there are Three Opinions about the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> the <hi>Roman,</hi> the <hi>Lutheran,</hi> and that <hi>of the Church of</hi> England, with thoſe that believe the ſame Doctrine. And if any one ſhould ask me, <hi>whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther theſe Opinions were within, or without the Church,</hi> I ſhould juſtly brand him with the Character of Impertinent, and think him not worth anſwering. It is ſuch a common form of expreſſing our ſelves, that I wonder how it could come into any Man's thoughts to cavil at it. But he adds, <hi>That which is more grievouſly ſuſpicious,</hi> (I wonder how he came to omit Heretical) <hi>is, that his Lordſhip calls the Catholick Faith, but a meer Opinion, and Perſuaſion of a Party.</hi> With what Confidence he aſſerts this, I can't imagine: He cannot ſhew me where the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop ſays, that <hi>the Catholick Faith is but a meer Opinion;</hi> for my part, I can ſee no ſuch thing throughout the whole Diſcourſe, no more than I can find that he ſays, 'tis <hi>the Perſuaſion of a Party.</hi> I ſuppoſe he had a mind that the Biſhop ſhould have ſaid it, and ſince he has not, he is ſo kind as to do it for him: For the Biſhop in his Preface calls it, <hi>the great Article of Chriſtianity, its moſt important Head,</hi> and rejects the <hi>Pacificatory Doctrines of thoſe who think that a diverſity of Opinions may be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured upon thoſe Heads, without breaking Communion about them.</hi> He ſays, <hi>they ſeem to be the Fundamentals of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity.</hi> And he thus concludes his Diſcourſe upon this Head: <hi>This Doctrine is ſo plainly ſet down in the New Teſtament, that if the Socinians Expoſitions are to be admitted, it will be hard to preſerve any Reſpect for it, or to believe thoſe Books writ with the common Degrees of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty and Diſcretion, not to ſpeak of Inſpiration.</hi> And all this is very fully repeated in the Biſhop's Letter to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:95617:5"/> Dr. <hi>Williams:</hi> So that to infer from his ſtating this matter at firſt, as <hi>a Third Opinion,</hi> that he thought it to be no more than <hi>an Opinion,</hi> is a Strain as unjuſt, as it is malicious. All that the Biſhop ſays of <hi>Opinion,</hi> is no more than this; <hi>viz. The third Opinion is, that the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 31.</note> 
               <hi>by the Eternal Word,</hi> &amp;c. And a little after, <hi>by thoſe of this Perſuaſion,</hi> &amp;c. And then a little after he adds, <hi>That this is the Doctrine I intend now to explain to you.</hi> And then, after he has explain'd it according to the Senſe of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> he calls it <hi>the received Doctrine;</hi> by which he can only mean, (nor can any one elſe give another Interpretation of it, than) the Article of our Faith, which we profeſs to believe and defend. I would willingly know where is the hurt of all this, in ſaying (as I before mentioned) that there are Three Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions concerning Chriſt's Preſence in the Sacrament, one of which is that of our Church, which I am fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded, is a Doctrine revealed in the Scriptures, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the Authority of the Primitive Fathers. Dares any one, I ſay, after all this, urge that I aſſert this only as a new Opinion and Perſuaſion of a Party? And if the Biſhop does not ſay as much concerning the Trinity, I deſire to lie under no better an Imputation, than our Author has very juſtly deſerv'd, of ſtating other Mens Doctrines falſly and by halves, according as the Byas of his preſent Inclinations turn'd him. I could not imagine that ever Prejudice or Ill Nature, ſhould ſo far blind and miſlead a Man, as to hurry him into wilful Errors, againſt the cleareſt Convictions both of Senſe and Reaſon. Don't we ſay every Day, that there are ſo many Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons about the firſt Origin of Things, the <hi>Ariſtotelick, Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curean, Chriſtian,</hi> &amp;c. and yet after all, we acknowledge that the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> is the only true Doctrine. God forbid, that every Man that mentions Opinion after that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, ſhould commit a Sin. For if he does, I know none that can pronounce themſelves Guiltleſs. Our Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, after this, ſpends a Page or two, in ſhewing the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Opinion;</hi> which Paper I think might have been better ſpared, ſince it is nothing to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95617:6"/> his purpoſe. For I know no where that the <hi>Biſhop</hi> aſſerts <hi>Opinion</hi> to be <hi>Faith;</hi> and if he had, he might have been better and more clearly convinc'd of his Error, by a few Pages in Biſhop <hi>Pearſon</hi> on the <hi>Creed,</hi> than in a dark obſcure Author. But after all, our <hi>Vindicator</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges <hi>that his Lordſhip ſometimes calls it Doctrine;</hi> but this term, ſays he, <hi>is Equivocal, and agrees as uſually to the Opinions of the Philoſophers.</hi> But here I muſt deſire to know of our Critick, whether ever he met with the Word <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> when it was applied in a Divinity Diſcourſe to the <hi>Tenets of the Church,</hi> to be meant of a Philoſophical Opinion; or when a Man is talking of the <hi>Doctrine of the Trinity, of the Incarnation and Divinity of Chriſt,</hi> he can at the ſame time refer it to the Opinions of <hi>Ariſtotle, Plato, Epicurus,</hi> or <hi>Carteſius.</hi> But it is the Fate of ſome of our over-grown Criticks, to catch at Shadows, when they can't lay hold of the Subſtance, and to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves appear in their own Colours, rather than ſay nothing.</p>
            <p>In the next Place, our Critick finds fault with the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop for ſaying, <hi>That we believe Points of Doctrine, becauſe</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 6.</note> 
               <hi>that we are perſuaded they are revealed to us in Scripture;</hi> which, he ſays, <hi>is ſo languid and unſafe a Rule, that it will reſolve Faith into every Man's private Fancie and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictory Opinions.</hi> Now I had thought hitherto, that the Scripture had been the adequate Meaſure and Rule of Faith, and that whatſoever we were perſuaded was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally contain'd in the Scriptures, we were oblig'd to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it. And though I am beholden to the univerſal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Church for my Belief that thoſe Books are the ſame that were delivered to us from the Apoſtles, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired Pen-men, yet I am oblig'd to believe nothing as an Article of Faith, but what I am perſuaded is revealed in Scripture. And certainly 'tis much more ſafe to rely upon the pure Word of God for the Truth of any Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, if I am convinc'd that it was Divinely Inſpired; than, as our Author would adviſe us, to depend upon the beſt Tradition and moſt unanimous Expoſition in the World: Since at length I muſt recur to the Scriptures
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:95617:6"/> to examine that Tradition by, and am no farther con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd to believe this, than I find it agreeable to the other. 'Tis true, that it is every Man's Duty to ſubmit to the unanimous Senſe of the Church, rather than to his own private Interpretation; but yet it is no farther, than he can find that Conſent agreeable to the revealed Will of God. And if this be not admitted as true Doctrine; I can't imagine how we could ever have arriv'd at this <hi>Happy Reformation,</hi> which we are now perſuaded was ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely neceſſary; ſince it could never have been effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, unleſs every Man has the Liberty of judging the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine he profeſſes, by the Teſtimony of the Scriptures: Nor are we to interpret the Scriptures ſo much by the Judgment of the Fathers and the Church, as we try theſe by their Harmony and Conſent with the former. And hence it will follow, that as we are not obliged to believe any thing which we think is contrary to Scripture; ſo whatſoever we do or ought to believe as an Article of Faith, we do it becauſe we are fully and clearly perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that it is revealed to us in the Scriptures. Elſe what ſhall thoſe do, who have no notion of Tradition, and have no other Rule to guide them, but the plain and direct Authority of God's Word? And though every Man is not to be his own Interpreter, yet he is to judge whether the received Interpretation is agreeable to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or not. If Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> had not here forgot the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Words of the Sixth Article of our Church, which tells us, <hi>That the Holy Scripture containeth all things neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for Salvation: So that whatſoever is not read therein, nor may be proved thereby, is not to be required of any Man, that it ſhould be believed as an Article of the Faith, or be thought requiſite or neceſſary to Salvation,</hi> he could not have run out ſo odly from it, or rather againſt it; it was the Foundation upon which the whole Reformation was built. If Univerſal Tradition in the Third, Fourth, and Fifth Centuries was a good Argument in it ſelf, then why was not Univerſal Tradition in the Thirteenth, Fourteenth, and Fifteenth Centuries as good a one? If the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a Doctrine lies in the Tradition of it, then all
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95617:7"/> Ages muſt be alike as to this. Therefore, tho' it is a noble Confirmation of our Doctrine, that we can appeal to the firſt Six Ages of the Church; yet if the Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that happen'd after the Sixth Century, had begun as early as the Third, this had not at all chang'd the Nature of things. And I believe it will be found a more ſimple and juſt way of interpreting Scripture, by other places of it more eaſily and plainly expreſs'd, than by any other Method that can be found out for that purpoſe. For if I am to judge of the Senſe of Scripture only by <hi>Tradition,</hi> and the Authority of the Fathers, I ſhall be often at a loſs, and it will be as difficult to me, to find out their Senſe and meaning, as it was that of the Text I was to enquire after: But of this enough. When I read this Criticiſm of our Vindicator's, I was inclin'd to think, he was, though perhaps unwittingly, ſet a work by the Papiſts, as I before imagin'd he was by the Socinians, to make Diviſions and Schiſms in the Church. And this I take to be Mr. <hi>Hill</hi>'s Orthodox Doctrine.</p>
            <p>But let us carry him to his next Criticiſm. <hi>His Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 8.</note> ſays he, <hi>is not clear in the point of Incarnation,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he tells us, that by the Union of the <hi>Eternal Word with Chriſt's Humanity, God and Man truly became One Perſon. Now here,</hi> ſays our Authour, <hi>we are not taught, whether there were three, or any one Perſon in the Godhead, before the Incarnation. For this account will admit the Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nality of Chriſt, to be founded firſt in the Humane Nature, according to ſome of his Lordſhip's Criticks, (which he dares not contradict) who place the foundation of the Sonſhip, in the lower Nature.</hi> This is ſtrange, when his Lordſhip ſays a while after, that <hi>Divine Perſon in whom dwelt the Eternal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 45.</note> 
               <hi>Word;</hi> Which makes him as well a Perſon before the Incarnation, as it does the ſecond Perſon in the Bleſſed Trinity; becauſe by the Eternal Word, is always under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the ſecond Perſon. And ſince his Lordſhip does allow him to be a <hi>Divine Perſon,</hi> as alſo to be <hi>Eternal,</hi> I wonder how any Man can imagine, that his Lordſhip does not teach any diſtinction in the Godhead before the Incarnation; or that the <hi>Perſonality of Chriſt,</hi> or the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:95617:7"/> foundation of the Sonſhip, was firſt placed in the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature: Since his calling him the <hi>Eternal Word,</hi> makes him a diſtinct <hi>Perſon</hi> from the <hi>Father</hi> from all <hi>Eternity,</hi> as being <hi>ſecond of the ever Bleſſed Trinity;</hi> and his ſtyling him a <hi>Divine Perſon,</hi> ſuppoſes the <hi>Perſonality</hi> of Chriſt to be firſt founded in the <hi>Godhead.</hi> For I ſhould have thought (had I not been prejudic'd by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of ill Nature) that Chriſt could be called a <hi>Divine Perſon,</hi> only upon the account of the <hi>Godhead dwelling</hi> in Fleſh, and not upon any account of his Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood: (For elſe there would be two Perſons in Chriſt.) And therefore I think, that the Biſhop can mean nothing elſe, but that he was a <hi>Divine Perſon,</hi> only as he was God; and conſequently ſo, before he was Incarnate, becauſe he was <hi>Eternal</hi> in the Biſhop's own Expreſſion. And therefore I may poſitively affirm, that our Author's Aſſertion, that the <hi>Biſhop's plain intention by theſe words, was to place Chriſt's Perſonality only in his Manhood,</hi> to be Falſe and Malicious. Yea, but ſays our Author, this deſcription of the Biſhop's, (viz. <hi>That by the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of the Eternal Word with Chriſt's Humanity, God and Man truly became one Perſon) will admit the Patripaſſian Hereſie, of but one Perſon in the Deity: For if the Eternal Word were no Perſon diſtinct from the Father, the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion thereof with the Humanity, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutes the Father an Incarnate Perſon; or otherwiſe by this ſtate of his Lordſhip's Doctrine, the Father, Son, and the Holy Ghoſt, may be conceived as one Incarnate Perſon.</hi> How our Critick came to think of this Remark, I can't appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend. For I never yet met with any Man, that thought the <hi>Eternal Word</hi> meant the whole Trinity; but that when the Eternal Word, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, was mentioned, it was always underſtood of the ſecond Perſon. And when we uſe that Expreſſion, we always think we have explain'd our ſelves, as much as though we had uſed the Name <hi>of tho ſecond Perſon in the Trinity.</hi> And the Biſhop does ſeem ſo plainly to mean this by it, that I wonder how any Man endued with Reaſon could force another Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of it. Eſpecially, when his Lordſhip in the very ſame Page, calls the <hi>Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:95617:8"/> 
               <hi>three Perſons by name,</hi> and ſhews how far they are diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſht the one from the other: Which Doctrine I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume is impoſſible ever to admit the Patripaſſian Hereſie of but one Perſon in the Deity, or to make the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt be conceived as one Incarnate Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; when at the ſame time the Biſhop affirms them to be Three Perſons: Which I muſt leave to our Author to reconcile. Nay in the ſame Page he has <hi>Perſon</hi> three times repeated, (which ſhews that he was not either afraid or unwilling to uſe that Expreſſion, as our Author would have us believe) beſides that which he applies particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly to the <hi>Incarnate Word;</hi> and in every one of theſe he refers to the <hi>Bleſſed Three.</hi> 1. He tells us of the Name <hi>Perſon</hi> being applyed to the <hi>Three.</hi> 2. He ſhews what is meant by <hi>Perſon,</hi> when it is applyed to the <hi>Three.</hi> 3. He tells us, <hi>that by explaining he does not mean, that be will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to tell us, how this is to be underſtood, and in what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect theſe Perſons are believed to be One, and in what reſpect they are Three.</hi> Now can any man after all this affirm, that his Lordſhips words <hi>would lead one to a Concluſion, or at leaſt a fair Jealouſie, that his Lordſhip does not believe any Diſtinction really Perſonal between the Father, Word, and Holy Spirit, but that the true and real Perſonality of Chriſt, is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to the Humane Nature?</hi> When he has been all along aſſerting a Perſonal Diſtinction in the <hi>Trinity,</hi> and made the Second Perſon in the <hi>Trinity</hi> (that is, the Incarnate Word) Eternal, as plain as words can make it. I ſhall add to this, as well as to ſome other of his bitter and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decent Reflections: <hi>What ſhall be given unto thee, or what ſhall be done unto thee thou falſe Tongue? Oh deliver my ſoul, O Lord, from lying lips, and from a deceitful tongue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have not time, or if I had, I ſhould not think it well ſpent, to take notice of every trivial Inſinuation of our Author's. I ſee no cauſe to believe that his Lordſhip has uſed the word <hi>Perſon</hi> in any different ſenſe, than what ours and the whole Catholick Church has ever uſed it; and if at any time he has omitted it, when he names the <hi>Bleſſed Three,</hi> yet he means as much by it as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture does, by his endeavouring to follow as much as may
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:95617:8"/> be the Scripture phraſe, and makes them as much differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent as the Church does when ſhe names the <hi>Perſons.</hi> And it is not only ſome ſly Inſinuations, and malicious Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions to the contrary, but direct Proofs and down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Arguments, and ſolid Reaſon that can ſatisfie any Impartial and Inquiſitive Mind. I ſhall here beg leave to uſe the Biſhop's own words, which in his Letter to Dr. <hi>Williams,</hi> he inſerts as a juſt Reflection upon the odd Comments of the <hi>Socinians;</hi> Namely, <hi>That the Beſt,</hi> (and I am ſure the faireſt) <hi>rule of Criticiſm, is to conſider the whole Thread, Strain, and Phraſeology of a Book, and not to deſcant upon the various ſignifications that the words themſelves taken ſeverally may be capable of.</hi> Had our Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick obſerv'd this Rule, he would never have troubled the World with his rude and confuſed Notions, nor have abuſed himſelf, as he hath now too inconſiderately done.</p>
            <p>But now let us ſee what our Vindicator has to urge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Biſhop's ſaying, <hi>That the Term Perſon came to</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 11.</note> 
               <hi>be applied to the Three, to diſcover thoſe, who thought that theſe Three were different names of the ſame thing, which were for the moſt part, and were generally called</hi> Patripaſſians, <hi>and were expelled as Hereticks from the Church.</hi> Now as to this, he takes up two or three Pages to ſay nothing, only to yield up the Cauſe, and yet to cenſure the Biſhop for ſaying the Truth. He quotes indeed a paſſage or two from <hi>Tertullian</hi> and <hi>Athanaſius;</hi> but for any thing that they are to his purpoſe, he might as well have quoted <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> or <hi>Seneca:</hi> He introduces them, to ſhew that the Term <hi>Perſon</hi> was then uſed, but not to prove that the occaſion of its uſe, was not upon account of the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tripaſſiun,</hi> or the like <hi>Hereſies.</hi> Now I would deſire him to produce any Author that aſſerts, that the word <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> was uſed before ſome <hi>Hereſie</hi> aroſe, that enforc'd the neceſſity of it. For if there is nothing more meant by ſaying that there are three Different <hi>Perſons</hi> in the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, than what the Scripture means by ſaying, that there <hi>are Three that bear Witneſs in Heaven,</hi> and elſwhere to the ſame purpoſe; there could be no neceſſity for
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:95617:9"/> uſing the Word Perſon to explain it, unleſs it was to ſatisfie and undeceive thoſe, who either doubted it, or denied the reality of any Perſonal Diſtinction. And if all Men had believed exactly, as the Scripture declares it ſelf, I may well ſuppoſe that the Term <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> might not have been made uſe of, at leaſt there would have been no neceſſity for it to this very Day. And though thoſe Hereticks that denied any Perſonal Diſtinction in the Godhead, denied the received Doctrine of the Church; yet does it not follow, as our Author would perſuade us, that the Word Perſon was before uſed; ſince, as was already ſaid, what the Scripture has revealed to us concerning that ſacred Myſtery, imports as much as what we mean by a <hi>Perſonal Diſtinction.</hi> From whence it follows, that ſince there was no occaſion for the uſe of it, 'tis very probable that Term was not, till ſome Hereſies broke out, introduc't into the Church; and if ſo, our Vindicator's, and not <hi>his Lordſhip's Inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation is falſe and injurious. Tertullian</hi> indeed, charges ſome with denying the <hi>Eternal Word</hi> to be <hi>a Subſtantial, Real Perſon:</hi> But this is only an interpretation of the Scripture, or ſeems deſign'd to ſhew in what Senſe he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands it. And if we ſhould grant that he was not the firſt that uſed it, yet it will not follow, but that there were Hereticks before, that denied any diſtinction in the Godhead which might give occaſion for the firſt uſe of it. I deny not, that the Word Perſon was uſed regularly in the Church, or that it is very expreſſive of the Senſe of the Scripture, and very agreeable to it; but only, that it does not appear that it was made uſe of, before ſome Hereſies or Diſputes aroſe about the Meaning of thoſe Places of Scripture, which made the uſe of it ſeem abſolutely neceſſary. And this, and no other, ſeems to be his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip's plain meaning. But had his Lordſhip ſhewn any diſlike to the uſe of it, which I don't any where find in his whole Diſcourſe the leaſt reaſon to ſuſpect; yet I find no leſs an Author than St. <hi>Hierom</hi> cited (by a late great Prelate, who always uſed that Word with a great deal of Approbation and Eſteem) as deſiring in ſome
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:95617:9"/> of his Writings to be excus'd mentioning it. Though I know this is nothing to the Purpoſe, yet I wonder our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor would let him eſcape without ſome Mark of Defama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as ſeeming to have a greater diſlike to that Term, than the Biſhop has any where expreſt, and therefore a fitter Subject to vent his Paſſion againſt.</p>
            <p>But to go on: In his next Paragraph, he comes to<note place="margin">Pag. 15.</note> ſhew us, that his Surmiſes againſt his Lordſhip's Integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty are well grounded, by his Lordſhip's Explanation of the Term <hi>Perſon.</hi> For by <hi>Perſon,</hi> ſaith his Lordſhip, <hi>is only meant, that every one of the Bleſſed Three, has a peculiar Diſtinction in himſelf, by which he is truly different from the other Two.</hi> Here, ſays our Author, it is plain, <hi>That by uſing the Term Three ſo often, without adding Perſon, he ſhuns the Word as much as he dares at preſent to do, and aſſigns a Diſtinction, which is not any way Perſonal.</hi> Now as to his ſhunning the Word <hi>Perſon,</hi> I think there is no reaſon to ſuſpect, when he had uſed it but in the ſame Sentence, that our Author finds fault with; and I may offer to ſay, that he could not there have properly uſed it oftner. But I ſuppoſe our Author would have had his Lordſhip ſay, that by, there being <hi>Three Perſons</hi> in the Godhead, is to be underſtood that thoſe <hi>Perſons are Three:</hi> For otherwiſe, how his Lordſhip's Explanation is Faulty I can't ſee. And if his <hi>Lordſhip dares not make it his own,</hi> or <hi>allow it for proper,</hi> as the Vindicator maliciouſly inſinuates, yet there are others that dare. Without doubt, as our Author would have it, 'tis the beſt Definition in the World of <hi>Ens,</hi> to ſay it is <hi>Ens,</hi> and that an <hi>Individuum</hi> is an <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viduum:</hi> How we can otherwiſe explain, there being <hi>Three Perſons</hi> in the Godhead, I can't imagine, <hi>but by ſaying they are really diſtinct from each other.</hi> And our Author's fine turn <hi>of three Tobacco Pipes,</hi> may as well refer to the Apoſtle's ſaying, <hi>there are Three that bear witneſs in Heaven;</hi> as to any thing his Lordſhip has ſaid; and then he might have added Blaſphemy to his Nonſenſe. Yes, but ſays our Author, his Lordſhip ſhould have added in his Definition of the Term <hi>Perſon,</hi> the Words of <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Son,</hi> and <hi>Holy Ghoſt.</hi> Now I can tell our Author
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:95617:10"/> that this Anſwer is to be made to thoſe who enquire who are the <hi>Three</hi> that conſtitute the <hi>Godhead,</hi> and not to what we mean by <hi>Perſon,</hi> when we apply it to them as ſuch. For when we conſider them as <hi>Perſons,</hi> there is no neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, that we ſhould in the ſame Breath, explain the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation they bear to each other. And though they are Three Perſons, as being <hi>Father, Son,</hi> and <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> yet that would be no direct Anſwer to the Queſtion, What we mean by Perſon, when we apply it to the Bleſſed Three? And if our Vindicator had truly conſidered this, he might have ſtopt his Fury for a Page or two together. <hi>When I firſt read this, I thought it might be the ſlip of an angry haſty Pen; but when I conſidered it was of the ſame ſtrain with the reſt of the Book, a great deal ſaid upon nothing, I concluded, that it muſt proceed either from groſs Ignorance, or inveterate Malice. I ſuſpect ſomething more than ſhould be. I am ſure the whole Foundation is rotten, and more than tacitely imports a Renunciation of all Charity, the greateſt</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 17.</note> 
               <hi>Branch of our Chriſtianity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In his next Paragraph, he comes to give up the Cauſe; for he tells us, that by the <hi>Biſhop's calling them the Bleſſed Three, he means as much as we do by Perſons; becauſe,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>when applied to every of the Three, muſt mean the ſame as we do by Perſon;</hi> and if ſo, the only quarrel is about Words, and not the Senſe of the thing; and I know no reaſon why his Lordſhip ſhould be cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured for not mentioning <hi>Perſon</hi> in every Line, when every where he means the ſame as we do by it, and has expreſt himſelf in the ſame Terms as the Scripture has done. And I much wonder why Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> did not cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chize the Apoſtle for not uſing the Word <hi>Perſon,</hi> (as he very ridiculouſly expoſes himſelf) ſince there is as much reaſon for the one, as the other. But beſides, his Lordſhip has ſeveral times mentioned <hi>Perſon</hi> in relation to the Trinity, which none of the Apoſtles or Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts have ever done: But had he not done it, yet the Reaſon which he gives in anſwer to his Socinian Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, may be ſufficient to excuſe it. And therefore, I ſhall here beg leave to tranſcribe thoſe Words. <hi>When
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:95617:10"/> Chriſt commanded all to be Baptized, in the Name of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 99, 100.</note> 
               <hi>Son, and Holy Ghoſt, he plainly mentioned Three; if therefore I, to adhere to Scripture Terms, had avoided the frequent uſe of any other Word but the Three, I thought how much ſoever this might offend others, who might apprehend that I ſeem'd to avoid mentioning of Trinity or Perſons (which yet I ſhewed flowed from no diſlike of thoſe Words, but meerly that I might ſtick more exactly to Scripture Terms) yet I had no reaſon to think that Men of the other ſide would have found ſuch Fault with this: Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt are the Three of whom I diſcourſe; ſo inſtead of repeating theſe Words at every time, I ſhorten'd it, by ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Bleſſed Three. Now it is a ſtrain particular to our Author, who I ſuppoſe had it from the Socinian Writer to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large on this.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now let us look into our Author, and ſee if he is not guilty of as great Faults or Hereſies, as thoſe which he falſly objects againſt the Biſhop. His Lordſhip's<note place="margin">Pag. 22, 23.</note> Words which he cenſures are theſe; <hi>The Second of this Bleſſed Three was united to a perfect Man,</hi> (that is, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our Author's own Interpretation, the Second Perſon in the Holy Trinity, took our Fleſh, which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly follows from his Criticiſm upon <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſo that from the Humane and Divine Nature thus united, there did reſult the Perſon of the Meſſias, who was both God and Man.</hi> This he condemns as falſe Doctrine, becauſe it denies the <hi>Perſonality of Chriſt to be Eternal;</hi> but if this be falſe Doctrine, I deny it too: For I nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther acknowledge or believe, that Chriſt, who was God and Man, was Eternal: but only <hi>the Second Perſon in the Trinity,</hi> who in the fulneſs of time took our Fleſh, and by that Union became Chriſt, our Anointed High Prieſt, and the Meſſias that was to come into the World. And I dare poſitively affirm, that from this Union reſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Perſonality of Chriſt, that is, the Meſſias; though our Vindicator of the Doctrine of the Church, and the Ancient Fathers, does poſitively deny it. His Words are theſe; <hi>That though the Character and Offices of Chriſt reſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 23.</note> 
               <hi>from the Incarnation, yet not the Perſon or Perſonality.</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:95617:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> Now I would deſire to know whether this is the Doctrine of our Church; if not, 'tis Hereſie, and deſtroys the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality of the Incarnation. <hi>The Athanaſian Creed,</hi> which we profeſs to adhere to, makes <hi>Perſonality</hi> to <hi>conſiſt in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of God and Man:</hi> As thus; <hi>Who although he be God and Man, perfect God and perfect Man, God of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Father, and Man of the Subſtance of his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yet he is not two, but one Chriſt.</hi> And thus it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained; <hi>For as the reaſonable Soul and Fleſh,</hi> if ſeparated and taken apart, make two diſtinct Subſtances; yet as they are united, are but one Man or Perſon; ſo, that is, after the ſame manner, <hi>God and Man, (of a reaſonable Soul, and humane Fleſh ſubſiſting,</hi> which takes in the whole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Man) <hi>is one Chriſt.</hi> And although he was God, the Second Perſon from all Eternity; yet, before he took the <hi>Manhood into God,</hi> he could not be the <hi>Perſon Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> or the <hi>Meſſias.</hi> Our Author very confidently and erroneouſly affirms, that the aſſumption of the Humane Nature to the Divine, contributed nothing of Perſonality to the Meſſias: But certainly the <hi>Athanaſian Creed,</hi> if Words were deſign'd to expreſs the Senſe of a thing, teach the directly contrary Doctrine. For why ſhould it ſay, that God and Man is one Chriſt, if it did not mean that the compleat Perſon of Chriſt reſulted from that union? I would ask our Author, whether the Man <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> be a Perſon or not? If he be; whether it is only as he is God, or Man, or as he is both? If he is only as he is <hi>God,</hi> what becomes of the Man, and of the Subſtance which he had of his Mother? For if it does not enter into the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonality, it is nothing, but an accident that might be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed at Pleaſure; and yet the Meſſias, that is <hi>perfect God, and perfect Man,</hi> ſhould remain the ſame <hi>Perſon</hi> ſtill. Now I wonder with what Confidence, a Man that pretends to vindicate the Ancient Doctrine of the Church, to cenſure others for Hereſle, and to refer his Vindications <hi>to the Senſe and Judgment of the Church <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal, the Archbiſhops and Biſhops of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>the two fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities, and the next Seſſion of Convocation;</hi> ſhould deny an Ancient Doctrine of the Church, the direct
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:95617:11"/> Senſe of the great and moſt Orthodox <hi>Athanaſius</hi> (which the Creed, ſo called, is ſuppoſed to be the Summ of) and the preſent Faith and Perſuaſion of our own Church of <hi>England;</hi> which God grant may long ſtand fixt and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>movable, in the Simplicity and Purity of its Primitive Doctrine, againſt all falſe Pretenders to Truth, and all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable Cenſurers of its Faith.</p>
            <p>But we have not yet done with his Errors. In the<note place="margin">Pag. 23.</note> ſame Paragraph he tells us, <hi>That though the Character and Offices of Chriſt reſulted from the Incarnation, yet not the Perſon or Perſonality; for to this the Humane Nature was aſſumed or pre-exiſtent.</hi> If the Humane Nature was aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed to Chriſt, then he was Chriſt, that is, the Meſſias, before he was Incarnate; which is unintelligible. What he means by the Humane Nature's being pre-exiſtent to the Perſonality or Perſon of Chriſt, I can't find. If he believes that the Humane Nature of Chriſt did exiſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was united to the Godhead, I preſume 'tis down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Hereſie; for that makes them two diſtinct Perſons; at leaſt it makes him the Meſſias before the union of both Natures. But beſides, as ſoon as Chriſt was born, he was ſtiled Chriſt the Lord, by way of Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence; to ſhew that he was then truly God; and that he was Chriſt our Saviour only by that Union of both Natures in him, and not before. And therefore I preſume, that the Humane Nature did <hi>not pre-exiſt, before he was one altogether, not by confuſion of Subſtance, but by unity of Perſon.</hi> Whatever he means by this Term, I can find nothing but down-right Abſurdity and Contradiction in it. Now I was much wondring how our Author came to light upon this Notion; That <hi>nothing of the Perſonality of Chriſt reſulted from the Humane Nature:</hi> But finding by the Thread of his Diſcourſe, that he had read ſomewhere, that when two contrary Qualities meet together, that which is the predominant wholly deſtroys the other; hereupon he concludes, that in the Union of God and Man, the former, being the more prevalent; deſtroyed the latter; and conſequently, there could reſult no Perſonality from that Nature which
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:95617:12"/> was deſtroyed, I was almoſt brought over to his Opinion; and I found it to be ſuch a pretty Philoſophical Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, that I durſt not venture to attack it. I ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this with this Sentence, which is amongſt the Works of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> though aſcribed to another: <hi>Siquis confite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Filium Dei, quaſi Phantaſma, ſic in Carne viſum fuiſſe, Anathema illi, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But however, we muſt not yet leave him: Let us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore<note place="margin">Pag. 25.</note> ſee his Remark upon his Lordſhip's ſaying, <hi>That we believe that Chriſt was God, by Vertue of the indwelling of the Eternal Word. The</hi> Jews <hi>could make no Objection to this, who knew that their Fathers had Worſhipped the Cloud of Glory, becauſe of God's reſting upon it.</hi> By which, ſays our Author, <hi>he lays a Foundation on which we may properly Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie Chriſt's Humane Nature.</hi> Here I muſt inform our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, that by <hi>indwelling,</hi> I ſuppoſe his Lordſhip under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands the Preſence of God, and not the Place or Habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion where he dwells; and that for this Reaſon, becauſe his Lordſhip had before told us, <hi>That a conſtant and immediate viſible indwelling of the</hi> Jehovah, <hi>was according to Scripture Phraſe ſaid to be</hi> Jehovah, <hi>which was applyed to nothing elſe.</hi> By which his Lordſhip can only mean, that that Appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance was always taken to be God, by which he did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiate himſelf. And if ſo, as I believe every rational Man that conſiders it will imagine, we could have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpens'd with our Author's omitting his little Criticiſms up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Habitation, Reſident, Reſidence, and the like.</hi> For by the<note place="margin">Pag. 28.</note> Cloud of Glory, his Lordſhip ſeems only to mean the <hi>Sche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinah,</hi> which the <hi>Rabbins,</hi> according to our Author's own Confeſſion, interpret <hi>that Lucid Glory, by which God preſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated himſelf:</hi> And if this Interpretation be allowed, as I know not how it can be denied, I know no reaſon why <hi>Schechinah</hi> may not be taken figuratively for <hi>Jehovah.</hi> And though <hi>Schechinah</hi> may be ſometimes called the <hi>Glory of the Jehovah;</hi> yet there is no reaſon why it may not in a different expreſſion ſignifie <hi>Jehovah,</hi> as well as <hi>Infinite Power, Majeſty,</hi> and the like, are often us'd to ſignifie <hi>God,</hi> though we often call him a <hi>God of infinite Power and Majeſty.</hi> And though it would be very abſurd to ſay,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:95617:12"/> infinite Power of Infinite Power, or O Infinite Majeſty, ſhew me thy Majeſty, as our Author plays upon Words, yet it would be Senſe to ſay, <hi>O Infinite Majeſty,</hi> ſhew me thy <hi>ſelf,</hi> thy <hi>Glory;</hi> which I take to be meant of God himſelf; as ſeems to be plain in that place where <hi>Moſes</hi> deſires to ſee the <hi>Glory of God;</hi> which is truly meant of God himſelf, notwithſtanding all our Author ſays to the contrary; as is plain by God's telling him, that he <hi>ſhould ſee his back parts;</hi> but his Face ſhould not be ſeen; that is, in a direct Anſwer to part of <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Requeſt, that he ſhould ſee the back Parts of his Glory; ſo that if this Senſe be admitted, as I don't ſee it can be denied, our Critick's impenetrable Syllogiſm, as he calls<note place="margin">Pag. 26</note> it, will vaniſh, with all his other ſophiſticated Shews of Arguments.</p>
            <p>But now that we may ſee what a mighty knack at In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention our Author has attain'd to; he comes now to make the Biſhop ſpeak things, which I believe I may po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitively affirm were never in his Thoughts, I am ſure they<note place="margin">Pag. 30.</note> are not in his Book: That is, he has a mind the Biſhop ſhould aſſert ſuch things; and ſince he does not, he finds he is able to do it for him, and therefore he reſolves that the Biſhop ſhall own them. It is a very pretty way of anſwering an Adverſary, to make falſe Doctrine for him, and then to cenſure it: For here he brings in the Biſhop to affirm, <hi>That in Scripture Phraſe,</hi> Jehovah <hi>never imports any thing elſe, but a conſtant and viſible immediate Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation;</hi> and when he has made this Speech for his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, it is eaſily imagin'd into what Abſurdities he leads him. Now our Author would have done fairly, to have told us where the Biſhop ſays this, and to have quoted the Place from whence he had it: I muſt confeſs, I can find no ſuch thing in all the Biſhop's Diſcourſe. 'Tis true, his Lordſhip ſays, <hi>that a conſtant and immediate vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible indwelling of the</hi> Jehovah, <hi>was according to Scripture Phraſe ſaid to be</hi> Jehovah, <hi>which was applyed to nothing elſe.</hi> But does it hence follow, that where ever the Name <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah</hi> is uſed in Scripture, it is, according to the Biſhop, applied to this <hi>Indwelling:</hi> Our Author might have as
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:95617:13"/> well argued, and with as much reaſon, that becauſe eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Man</hi> is an <hi>Animal,</hi> therefore every <hi>Animal</hi> is a <hi>Man:</hi> For to me it ſeems an exact parallel Caſe. I dare not do our Author ſo much Injuſtice as to call his Logick in queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, becauſe he ſeems to have a particular knack at Syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſing; but I muſt needs tell him, that there is great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for queſtioning his Integrity.</p>
            <p>I come now to conſider another Criticiſm of our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor's,<note place="margin">Pag. 32.</note> upon theſe Words of his Lordſhip's; <hi>viz. That Chriſt was God by Vertue of the indwelling of the Eternal Word in him; that the</hi> Jehovah <hi>dwelt ſo immediately and bodily in Chriſt Jeſus, that by that indwelling he was truly</hi> Jehovah: And again, as in another Place, <hi>that he was the true</hi> Jehovah, <hi>by a more perfect indwelling of the Deity in him, than that had been which was in the Cloud.</hi> Now this, ſays our Author, <hi>muſt be grounded upon a Principle or Maxim, that whatſoever the Deity immediately Inhabits, that thing becomes God, and the true</hi> Jehovah, <hi>by Vertue of that Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation.</hi> I anſwer, that his Lordſhip needs not ground his Aſſertion upon any ſuch <hi>Principle</hi> or <hi>Maxim,</hi> foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as he affirms, <hi>that Chriſt was the True</hi> Jehovah <hi>by a more perfect indwelling of the Deity in him, than that which was in the Cloud:</hi> The latter being temporary, and as it began to be given in the Wilderneſs, ſo was to diſconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue. But the <hi>indwelling of the Eternal Word in</hi> Chriſt, is<note place="margin">Pag. 35.</note> Eſſential and inſeparable, and conſtitutes with the Manhood one and the ſame Perſonality. And I know not how this is Heretical, or <hi>can juſtifie Idolatry,</hi> as our Vindicator would inſinuate: But if every thing muſt be Hereſie and Idolatry which an angry Man is reſolv'd to make ſo, I know nothing but may be perverted to ſuch a Senſe; ſince the greateſt Truths muſt appear directly contrary, if he may have the Liberty of putting what Gloſſes he pleaſes upon it, and if the World will be ſo good natur'd as to believe that its true and genuine Feature, which he makes it appear in.</p>
            <p>And now it is time to ſee, upon what account our Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicator is moved with Indignation, at his Lordſhip's ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>that</hi> Jehovah <hi>was a foederal Name of God, which being
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:95617:13"/> generally tranſlated by <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in the Septuagint, which Name was applyed to our Saviour in the New Teſtament by way of Eminence, to ſhew that he was the true</hi> Jehovah, <hi>who was called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> always in the Septuagint Tranſlation.</hi> Now though our Author does ſeem to approve of the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment drawn from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, yet he is angry that his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip ſhould call <hi>Jehovah</hi> a federal Name of God. And his Reaſons are, becauſe he was called <hi>Jehovah</hi> by <hi>Balaam,</hi> and alſo by <hi>Job,</hi> who were in no Covenant with him. Now as to <hi>Balaam,</hi> we may anſwer, that he ſpeaks of <hi>Jehovah as the God of Iſrael:</hi> And his Words<note place="margin">Numb. 23, 21.</note> are, <hi>Jehovah his God is with him;</hi> which ſeem directly to mean, <hi>that their God, who by them is called</hi> Jehovah, <hi>is with them;</hi> and if he did not mean ſo, why did he ſay any thing more, than <hi>his God is with him?</hi> Whence it ſeems plain, that he means by it, that the God who was more peculiarly ſtyled <hi>Jehovah</hi> amongſt them, was ready to help and defend them: And it is very probable, that the Name was only known amongſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> by the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſignification of it, according to Dr. <hi>Lightfoot,</hi> which was <hi>faithful in performing what he had promiſed;</hi> that is, in keeping the Promiſes made to <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> concerning their Seed. And though that Name is alſo mentioned in <hi>Job,</hi> yet it is certain, that <hi>Job</hi> could not come by it, unleſs he had it from ſome particular Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation from God: And therefore in anſwer to our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, I will venture to advance this probable Account of it; That though <hi>Job,</hi> as is now generally believ'd, liv'd in the time of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> Bondage in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and was not in the ſame Covenant with them, yet the <hi>Jews</hi> meeting with the Hiſtory of him, might change the Name of God into that of <hi>Jehovah,</hi> and probably <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf might do it: or if the Author or Tranſlator of that Book was <hi>Moſes,</hi> or one of the Jewiſh Nation, he to make the whole Old Teſtament of a Piece, might call God by the Name of <hi>Jehovah,</hi> tho' neither <hi>Job</hi> nor his Friends knew any thing of it; as alſo thereby to ſhew the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> and others, that it was the ſame <hi>Jehovah</hi> who was their God, and in covenant with them, leaſt the People, who were
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:95617:14"/> very prone to Idolatry, ſhould think it was ſome other God, who had brought ſuch ſtrange things to paſs, and thereupon pay Adoration to him. Theſe are the two chief Arguments our Author inſiſts upon; All the reſt are very little, if at all to his purpoſe. And ſeeing his<note place="margin">Pag. 90.</note> Lordſhip in anſwer to his Socinian Adverſary, anſwer'd this Objection which our Vindicator makes, I ſhall no longer dwell upon it. And if our Author has no better Objections to urge, I don't ſee what reaſon he has to call it a <hi>federal Whimſie.</hi> Here I can't help obſerving our<note place="margin">Pag. 45.</note> Author's concluſion of this Paragraph; which may ſerve as a convincing Argument, that all our Author ſays, is the Reſult of Malice and ill Nature, which ſeem to be the only Cauſes, and not the falſe Doctrine of his Lordſhip's Diſcourſe, that firſt perſuaded him to appear in Publick, and to let the World ſee <hi>what manner of Spirit he was of. And therefore,</hi> ſays he, <hi>after all his Lordſhip's critical Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling, he wiſely comes to ſay a great many Good and Orthodox Truths on this Article, ſo far as that, that Chriſt was God, who manifeſted himſelf in our Fleſh, which being ſo diſſonant to all his former Modes of Expreſſions and avowed Notions</hi> (which, what they are, God only knows, I ſee nothing contrary to the true Doctrine of the Church) <hi>ſeem to have dropt from him, either unawares, or for a Colour of Defence againſt a foreſeen Charge of Hereſie</hi> (which certainly he had no reaſon to fear, ſince it doth not appear, that he hath hitherto ſaid any thing that looks in the leaſt that way) <hi>or perhaps the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Providence of God might ſo over-rule the Madneſs of the Prophet, to make him ſpeak that for the Chriſtian Faith, which he had no mind to, that his manifeſt Inconſiſtences might render him of no Authority for the uſe of Hereticks, either in preſent or future Ages.</hi> I think I need make no Anſwer to this, or bring againſt this moſt uncharitable, and undeſerved Calumny, any railing Accuſation, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay, <hi>the Lord rebuke him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now, that we may end the firſt part of this falſly ſtyled <hi>Vindication,</hi> let us conſider the Anſwer that he makes to his Lordſhip's Argument for the Deity of Chriſt,<note place="margin">45, 46.</note> which is, <hi>that the</hi> Jews <hi>and Apoſtates from Chriſtianity ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:95617:14"/> charged the Apoſtles nor Church with Idolatry or Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Worſhip, which they would certainly have done, had the Chriſtian Principles been Arian or Socinian.</hi> Againſt this our Vindicator urges, that it was <hi>the common Opprobrium both of Jews and Gentiles, and perfect Apoſtates, that the Chriſtians ador'd a meer Malefactor, which was certainly an imputation of Creature Worſhip: And that the</hi> Jews <hi>ever did,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 47.</note> 
               <hi>and do at this day, charge us with the Worſhip of a vile Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, who really (as they think) had no Deity in him; elſe, had they alſo thought him to be God, they had been,</hi> ipſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto, <hi>converted to us, the want of this Faith, being the only Bar to their Converſion, and the Cauſe why they execrate both our Lord and us for this very Doctrine.</hi> And then he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes very triumphantly; <hi>So unlucky is his Lordſhip, even</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 48.</note> 
               <hi>in the faireſt part of this Diſcourſe, as if God had laid this Curſe on him, that he that had ſophiſtically handled the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith in moſt part of it, ſhould not have the Glory or Comfort of having ſerv'd it, in any one Particular.</hi> Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, any one that reads this, would imagine that the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop was the moſt profligate Enemy to the Chriſtian Faith that ever appeared againſt it. But if we can find no juſt ground for ſuch opprobrious Speeches, then cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the Author of them <hi>has the greater Sin.</hi> Now I will readily grant, with our Author, that the <hi>Jews</hi> did not believe our Saviour to be God, but only that he was a meer Man; nor do I find that his Lordſhip denies it: All that I perceive his Lordſhip intends by it, is, that the <hi>Jews</hi> expected their <hi>Meſſias</hi> ſhould be <hi>God;</hi> and that upon ſuppoſition it was he that was come into the World, they did not urge it as Idolatry to worſhip him, which certainly they would have done, had they thought he would have been a meer Man, or a God only by <hi>Office,</hi> as the Socinians would have him, and not from all Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity coeſſential with the Father. Now I leave any Man to judge, if this does not ſeem to be a juſt Account, and a fair Interpretation of his Lordſhip's Argument. For I ſuppoſe, no one can think, that the Biſhop deſign'd by it, to ſhew that the <hi>Jews</hi> did really believe our Saviour to be the true Meſſias, and at the ſame time to reject
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:95617:15"/> him; but only that if they had not expected their Mef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias ſhould be God, they would have charged the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and the Church with Idolatry in worſhiping him, whom, though they had granted to be the Meſſias, yet they own'd to be no more than Man, as they expected their Meſſias to be. And this ſeems to be ſuch a convincing Argument for eſtabliſhing the Deity of Chriſt, as the <hi>Socinian</hi> Author durſt not venture to attack it; which unqueſtionably he would have done, could he have forc'd ſuch a Senſe on his Lordſhip's Words, or have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood them in the ſame manner, as our Author has done. And whoever will read the Biſhop's Anſwer to his <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> Adverſary in his Letter to Dr. <hi>Williams,</hi> muſt, I think, be neceſſarily convinc'd, that his Lordſhip meant no otherwiſe by that Paſſage, than I have interpreted it.</p>
            <p>And thus have I done with the firſt part of our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor's pretended <hi>Vindication:</hi> I have conſidered every Objection that he has made, have given it its full force and weight, that he may not complain of any injuſtice done him, or that his Senſe has been confounded, or his Meaning repreſented falſly and by halves, as he has in ſeveral Places, very apparently, and too maliciouſly ſerv'd his Lordſhip's Diſcourſe. For, as I have no other Aim or Deſign in this, but the plain Diſcovery of Truth, ſo have I nothing beſide that to byaſs my Judgment on either ſide. And now I hope I may leave it to all unpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judic'd Enquirers after Truth, to judge, whether all thoſe hard Sayings, with which he has ſo rudely, and unlike a Chriſtian, eſpecially one of his Profeſſion, every where treated his Lordſhip, may be applauded as juſt, or cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured both as uncivil and unchriſtian. I muſt confeſs, that after I had made ſome progreſs in this Anſwer to his <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication,</hi> I had ſome Thoughts of laying it aſide; for I found it was ſo generally lookt upon as a Shuffage of ſcurrilous Expreſſions, that it would ſeem ſuperfluous to anſwer an Author that I found generally condemn'd: But when I conſidered, there be ſome who are ill natur'd enough to believe any Scandal that is caſt upon thoſe,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:95617:15"/> whom they are prejudic'd againſt, without conſidering the Cauſes of it; I thought I might do ſome Service, by endeavouring to undeceive thoſe who had been either wilfully prejudic'd, or inconſiderately ſurpriz'd, into a belief of ſuch ill natur'd Aſperſions.</p>
            <p>I come now to conſider our Vindicator's Second Part<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wherein he talks and quotes much, and yet, as I can find, nothing to the purpoſe. I ſhall paſs over all his unjuſt and uncharitable Reflections, and only enquire into the Cauſes which he grounds them upon. The firſt thing he carps at, is, his Lordſhip's ſaying, <hi>That he will not pretend to inform them, how that Myſtery is to be underſtood, and in what reſpect theſe Perſons are ſaid to be One, and in what reſpect they are Three. Now what does this intimate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 51, 52.</note> ſays our Author, <hi>but that it is not laid down in Scripture, in what reſpect the Perſons are One, and in what reſpect they are Three?</hi> If our Author is reſolv'd that every thing ſhall be meant according to his Interpretation of it, I have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more to ſay to him: But it ſeems obvious enough to me, that his Lordſhip only means by it, that he will not pretend to ſhew the Modes of their Exiſtence, and make the Myſtery comprehenſible to our Reaſon; which ſeems the direct Senſe of thoſe Words of the Biſhop's, <hi>That he will not pretend to inform them, how this Myſtery is to be underſtood;</hi> and which is alſo plain enough, by his Lordſhip's Words that immediately follow the other be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned; <hi>viz. By explaining a Myſtery, can only be meant the ſhewing how it is laid down and revealed in Scripture; for to pretend to give any other Account of it, is to take away its Myſteriouſneſs, when the manner how it is in it ſelf, is offer'd to be made intelligible.</hi> I ſhould have wonder'd how our Author could have forc'd any ill Senſe from theſe Words, had I not conſidered, that what was at firſt his Deſign, at laſt became his Intereſt, to make his Writings all of a Piece, and to diſcover the ſame evil Spirit throughout the whole.</p>
            <p>The next thing he cenſures his Lordſhip for, is, for<note place="margin">Pag. 54.</note> ſaying, <hi>That too many, both Ancients and Moderns, have perhaps gone beyond due Bounds, while ſome were pleaſed
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:95617:16"/> with the Platonical Notions of</hi> Emanations, <hi>and a Fecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity in the Divine Eſſence.</hi> Now what Error his Lordſhip has fallen into by this, I don't yet apprehend: He does not poſitively expreſs any diſlike to thoſe Notions, or that they are otherwiſe than innocent, if they are made uſe of by Men of ſound and orthodox minds, but only that they may have given Occaſion to ſome, who are leſs cautious than others, to form too groſs Conceptions of thoſe things, of which they can never have any adequate Idea. And, <hi>certainly ſome of the Fathers in this way of explaining this Matter, have ſaid many things which inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate that they believed an inequality between the Perſons and a ſubordination of the Second and Third to the Firſt.</hi> And this our Author does dot deny, but cites Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> to<note place="margin">Pag. 89.</note> confirm the Aſſertion of the Fathers, teaching a Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Gradation and Subordination in the Deity; which probably theſe Notions might give the firſt riſe and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to. And if this be ſo, our Author has only ſpent his time to give up a Cauſe, which he endeavours to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend. I ſuppoſe I need give no Anſwer to our Author's Reflection, upon what his Lordſhip ſays, <hi>viz. [That theſe thought there was a Production, or rather an Eduction of Two out of the Firſt, in the ſame manner that ſome Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers thought that Souls were propagated from Souls; and the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure by which this was explain'd, being that of one Candle being lighted at another, this ſeems to have given the riſe to thoſe Words, Light of Light.</hi>] Since our Author brings in <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian, Juſtin Martyr,</hi> and <hi>Tatian,</hi> with the ſame <hi>Similies,</hi> which I ſuppoſe is enough to his Lordſhip's purpoſe, and is an exact Confirmation of what his Lordſhip has ſaid. And I wonder, why our Vindicator ſhould find fault with his Lordſhip for calling them <hi>Conceits,</hi> when himſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes<note place="margin">Pag. 86.</note> with Dr. <hi>Bull,</hi> that thoſe <hi>Similies are Lame, and ſuch as he will not make out.</hi> I ſhall not enquire into the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal of that Expreſſion, <hi>Light of Light,</hi> in our <hi>Nicene Crede;</hi> for whatſoever it was that firſt occaſion'd it, 'tis nothing at all to our preſent purpoſe. Yet this is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that ſuch like <hi>Similies</hi> as the <hi>Biſhop</hi> mentions, were uſed by the <hi>Fathers</hi> in their Writings to explain their No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:95617:16"/> of that Myſtery by, as well before as after the <hi>Nicene Council,</hi> which makes his Lordſhip's Conjecture very probable.</p>
            <p>A great part of what remains of our Author, is ſpent in vindicating the Doctrine of the Trinity, againſt the Charge of Novelty, which he would have the World be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, the Biſhop alledges againſt it, and to ſhew that the <hi>Primitive Fathers</hi> believed it. But ſince I can find no ſuch thing in all the Biſhop's Diſcourſe, it will be unneceſſary to give anſwer to it. All that I can underſtand of the Biſhop's Words, is, that the Ancients in their Explanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Trinity, often differ'd from one another, and that thoſe who came after, endeavour'd by other Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planations to ſupply thoſe Defects, which ſome who went before them had been guilty of: Not that he means they believed differently concerning the Trinity; but only that they made uſe of different Modes of explaining their Notions concerning it. <hi>And the while Men go about to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain a thing, of which they can frame no diſtinct Idea, it is very natural for them to run out into a vaſt multiplicity of Words, into great length, and much Darkneſs and Confuſion: Many improper Similies will be urged, and often impertinent Reaſonings will be made uſe of. All which are the unavoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Conſequences of a Man's going about to explain to others, that which he does not diſtinctly underſtand himſelf.</hi> And what is there in all this, that charges the Doctrine of the Trinity with Novelty?</p>
            <p>I can't but obſerve our Author's Ingenuity, in ſaying, that his Lordſhip, in his <hi>Letter from</hi> Zurich, <hi>has expoſed that Paſſage in St.</hi> John'<hi>s Firſt Epiſtle, for doubted: There are Three that bear Witneſs in Heaven, The Father, the Word, and the Spirit; and theſe Three are one.</hi> Since his Lordſhip only tells us, that in ſome Manuſcripts it is to be found, and in others not; in moſt of which, he ſhews plainly that it was the Fault of the Copier that omitted it: And alſo ſeems ſufficiently to prove by the Authority of St. <hi>Hierom,</hi> whoſe Preface he there makes mention of, that it was left out by the <hi>Arians.</hi> But beſides, if I muſt be ſaid to expoſe every part of an Author for
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:95617:17"/> doubted, by ſaying, that it is not to be found in ſuch a MS. which perhaps has all the reſt, almoſt all the Authors in the World muſt ſuffer by it; ſince I can ſhew our Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicator ſome thouſands of MSS. which have only tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to us ſome ſmall parts of Authors, and have omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thoſe, which yet by the help of others we can prove to be genuine.</p>
            <p>I ſhall make no Obſervation upon this malicious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark of our Vindicator's. It may ſerve as a pregnant In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance with the reſt of the Vindication, of the great Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Malice and ill Nature of transforming every thing into that peculiar Shape which they are reſolved it ſhould appear in; and alſo to convince us, how little Credit we are to give to things, which our ſelves are not Witneſſes of, ſince there are ſo <hi>many Falſe Prophets gone out into the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I can't but take notice of the Learned and Ingenious Obſervation of our Vindicator upon his Lordſhip's Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mile, which he brought not to explain, but only to illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate in ſome meaſure the Doctrine of the Trinity, which he has tranſcribed at length. I ſhall only mention thoſe parts of it which our Author criticiſes upon. He denies<note place="margin">Pag. 104.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> and <hi>Will,</hi> which the Biſhop affirms to be <hi>different Modes of Thinking,</hi> to be ſuch, either as they <hi>are taken as Principles,</hi> or as they <hi>may be ſuppoſed as Acts of the Mind.</hi> Now here I ſuppoſe our Vindicator was loſt in his own beloved Notions; and I wiſh he had read over <hi>Mr.</hi> Lock'<hi>s Eſſay of Humane <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> and I believe he would, at leaſt might, have expreſs'd himſelf leſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſedly. For I ſuppoſe our Vindicator, like ſome others of his ſtamp, takes <hi>Volition</hi> to be a diſtinct Agent in us, <hi>which can command, obey, and perform ſeveral Actions as a diſtinct Being.</hi> And no wonder then if it is no Mode of Thinking. But certainly if we would ſpeak properly, <hi>Intellection</hi> and <hi>Volition,</hi> if they are conſidered as <hi>Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> if our Vindicator underſtands any thing by that Word, are only <hi>Powers of the Mind.</hi> But if they are reduced to Acts, they are then properly ſpeaking <hi>Modes of Thinking,</hi> and nothing more. But our Vindicator is mightily diſturb'd at the Biſhop's ſaying, That <hi>in Acts of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:95617:17"/> Memory, Imagination and Diſcourſe, there ſeems to be a mixture of both Principles, or a third that reſults out of them. For we feel a Freedom in one reſpect; but as for thoſe Marks that are in our Brain, that ſet things in our Memory, or fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh us with Words, we are neceſſary Agents, they come in our way, but we do not know how. We cannot call up a Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of things or Words at pleaſure; ſome Diſorder in our Mechaniſm hides or flattens them, which when it goes off, they ſtart up and ſerve us, but not by any Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Will.</hi> Now ſays our Critick to this, <hi>As for his Mixtures, I leave them purely to himſelf; but for his third reſulting Principle I am to ſeek. For it muſt be ſuch a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple that is neither free nor neceſſary, and ſuch a one as is hard to be got for Love or Mony.</hi> Nay, not ſo hard nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: For Mr. <hi>Lock</hi> tells us, in his <hi>Chapter of the Modes of Thinking,</hi> that this is what the <hi>French</hi> call <hi>Reſvery,</hi> but our <hi>Language has ſcarce a Name for it.</hi> Which I take to be a good Authority (to uſe our Author's own Words) <hi>in deſpight of a bad Judgment and defective Libraries.</hi> Which may teach our Author, if ever he writes more (which I pray God forbid, unleſs it be a Retractation of this ill-na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur'd Book) to do it with more Caution and Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And amongſt the reſt, this was one Reaſon why I firſt undertook this, ſince he tells us of another Treatiſe which he deſigns to publiſh, to beg of him for his own ſake, and for the Churches ſake, and for the ſake of his Brethren the Clergy, to conceal it: For I think it is enough for any Man <hi>ſemel inſanire,</hi> and to expoſe himſelf, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any regard to his own, or the Churches Honour.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not ſearch into our Author's Explication, as he calls it, of the Sacred Myſteries of the <hi>Ever-Bleſſed Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity;</hi> becauſe, as 'tis Foreign to the preſent purpoſe, ſo is it confuſedly dreſt up with his affected dark way of Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, that I could hardly read it with Patience; much leſs could I ſpend much time upon it, in conſidering every Paſſage of it.</p>
            <p>And now I ſhould have left him, but that I ſtill find him ſpitting his Venome at his Lordſhip, for ſaying, that ſome have thought that the Term <hi>Son</hi> did not at all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the <hi>Bleſſed Three,</hi> but only to our Saviour, as he
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:95617:18"/> was the <hi>Meſſias, the Jews having had this Notion of the Meſſias, that as he was to be the King of Iſrael, ſo was he to be the Son of God.</hi> Now does it appear from hence, that the Biſhop is a Favourer of this Opinion? Or that him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf does believe, that the <hi>Jews</hi> expected that their Meſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as ſhould not be God? As to the latter, it is plain that his Lordſhip believes the contrary, by what he has urged in Defence of our Lord's Divinity, that <hi>the Jews never objected Idolatry to the Chriſtians;</hi> which certainly they would have done, had they not expected their Meſſias ſhould be God. Nor does his Lordſhip aſſert the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, as is plain by what he adds, That if <hi>this be true, all the Speculations concerning an Eternal Generation</hi> (which is a Doctrine he ſeems every where to maintain) <hi>are cut off in the ſtrict Senſe of the Words.</hi> And therefore our Vindicator has no reaſon to ſay, That <hi>his Lordſhip has left this Doctrine in ſuſpenſe, whether it be true or no.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His laſt Criticiſm is upon his Lordſhip's Saying, That <hi>it may be juſtly queſtioned, whether by theſe they have made it better to be underſtood, or more firmly believed; or whether others have not taken advantage to repreſent theſe Subtilties as Dregs, either of</hi> Aeones, <hi>of the</hi> Valentinians, <hi>or of the</hi> Platonick <hi>Notions—And it being long before theſe Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries were well ſtated and ſettled, it is no wonder if many of the Fathers have not only differ'd from one another, but even from themſelves in ſpeaking upon this Argument.</hi> To this, ſays our Critick, after he has emptied himſelf of his foul Language, which he every where abounds with, That <hi>all theſe traduced Theories of Faith are univerſally profeſſed, and received in the whole Church of God, and have but a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry few Adverſaries.</hi> To this it may be anſwered, that the Doctrine of the Trinity has been, and is, univerſally receiv'd; nor does the Biſhop deny it; but that all thoſe Theories about the Modes and the Explanations of it, which ſome of the Fathers have left us, are not, may be very eaſily evinc'd. Nor do I think it is any great Blemiſh to the Fathers, or any Scandal caſt upon their Authority, which may be of dangerous Conſequence to the Searchers into Antiquity, as our Vindicator would inſinuate, to ſay, that the Fathers could not ſearch into the depth of that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:95617:18"/> Myſtery, and that they were often at a loſs in their Explana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of it, though they might believe it as firmly, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſame manner, as the Church Catholick now does. For though perhaps moſt of us believe that great Article according to the true Senſe of the Church, yet probably if we went to explain it, we ſhould all follow different Methods, and have far different Idea's from each other. Which may ſerve to convince us, how inſufficient the moſt Rational and Thinking of us are, to form any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Notions of thoſe things, which are ſo far above our Comprehenſions.</p>
            <p>I ſhall ſay nothing upon his Reflection upon Dr. <hi>Burnet's Remarks upon the Strong-Box Papers;</hi> for, as I have them not by me, ſo I find a great deal of Reaſon to miſtruſt our Author's Integrity in every one of his Quotations, which I have ſhewn have been very foul and unjuſt, often took by halves, and as often perverted to a wrong Senſe, directly contrary to the Author's meaning.</p>
            <p>And now it may be asked, Why one that has no Knowledge of the Biſhop (no more than from his Works) or of Mr. <hi>Hill,</hi> ſhould engage himſelf in a Diſpute, in which he is no way concerned? To this I can only an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, That I had no other Inducement to it, than the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation I had againſt ſuch an indecent and unchriſtian way of Writing, and ſuch falſe Reaſoning as the pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Vindication</hi> is made up of. I could ſcarce believe that a <hi>Clergy-man,</hi> had he not told us he was one in the <hi>Title Page,</hi> could have been guilty of ſo much Uncharitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as I every where find in his Book. And I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that I had much rather be guilty of an Error in my Judgment, than offend in the Breach of ſo great a Duty; which is ſo expreſly laid down in Scripture; and which ought to be one of the greateſt Characteriſticks of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, eſpecially of thoſe who are to inſtruct others in ſuch Fundamental Duties both by Doctrine and Practice. Becauſe thoſe who can't find out an Errour in our Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, can eaſily diſcover thoſe in our Practice; which every one that can read, may ſee too openly proſtituted in our Author's <hi>Vindication.</hi> At the <hi>horrour</hi> and juſt dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of which I leave him to the Great Judge of all the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:95617:19"/> Earth, who will recompence every Man according to his Works; and to the Cenſures of thoſe who have the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er here committed to them to puniſh the wrong-doers. Who I hope for the Churches ſake, as well as for the ſake of that right Reverend and Learned Perſon whom our Author deſign'd to caſt a Blot upon, will never ſuffer ſo much breach of Charity, ſo much malice and ill nature, ſuch groundleſs Falſities, and ſuch Unchriſtian Temper to eſcape unpuniſhed, unleſs prevented by as full and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick a Recantation, as his Offence hath been notorious.</p>
            <div type="postscript">
               <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
               <p>AFter I had ſent this up to <hi>London,</hi> I received a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular or two from a Gentleman, who aſſured me he had it from the Biſhops own mouth, relating to the preſent Diſpute, which I thought might be proper to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert. One is, that the true reaſon why he avoided repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the word <hi>Perſon,</hi> is this, that he was to inſtruct his Clergy how to deal with <hi>Socinians,</hi> who acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no Authority but Scripture, they muſt be only dealt with according to that Conceſſion. Therefore every thing was to be avoided, that was not <hi>in terminis</hi> in Scripture. Now when this Article is once proved, then the uſe of the Terms, <hi>Eſſence, Perſons, Hypoſtaſis,</hi> and <hi>Conſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial</hi> are to be juſtified, both by ſhewing that they are not contrary to the Scripture, but agreeing with it, and alſo by ſhewing that it is in the power of the Church, when no new Doctrine is pretended to be added to the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Faith, to make uſe of ſuch terms, as may be thought fit to prevent and diſcover all Equivocations. And ſince even the Name <hi>Perſona</hi> in <hi>Latin</hi> may ſignifie a Vizar or Repreſentation; if Hereticks had owned a fraudulent meaning in receiving this, it was in the power of the Church to have choſen another. So that tho' the Church can add no new Doctrine to that which is revealed, yet ſhe may uſe ſtricter terms when ſhe finds an abuſe in the uſe of larger ones.</p>
               <p>As for the reaſon that led him to give an account of the different ways uſed by the Ancients in explaining this
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:95617:19"/> Myſtery, it was only this, that the anſwer to the Dean of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s was writ in ſo particular a Style, that it was much read. He feared this might be carried far, to raiſe a fire in the Church, and to give the Enemies of the Faith a pleaſant Entertainment. So tho his Lordſhip was not of the Dean of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Opinion, yet he thought it was fit as well as juſt, to ſhew that great Authorities from the Ancients might be brought for it. His chief intent being to lay that heat, and to ſhew the inconvenience of going too far, or too poſitively in Explanations. So he mention'd only ſo much as might juſtifie that deſign. This is the foundation of all the ſtir that our Author has made, which as I am truly informed the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> and the reſt of the Biſhops look upon as a breach not only of Charity, but of the Order of the Church. For it is far from their thoughts that either a Biſhop, or even an Archbiſhop ſhould have a Priviledge to corrupt the Faith, and be ſafe when he has done it. As they ought to be the chief Conveyors of this Sacred <hi>Depoſitum,</hi> ſo if any of them ſhould ſo far betray his truſt, as to offer to corrupt it, he muſt be uſed with all ſeverity. But if ſuch a caſe ſhould happen, the method of proceeding ought to be a denunciation to the Archbiſhop, when it is in the caſe of a Biſhop. This ought to be firſt made to the Archbiſhop in private, and if that will not do, then it ought to be made in open Court by Articles. If any thing is taught contrary to the Doctrine of the firſt Four Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Councils, it is by Act of Parliament 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> Hereſie. And if it is contrary to the Creeds, then it falls under the Act of Uniformity. The Three Creeds being parts of the Book of Common-Prayer. And if any Doctrine is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Thirty nine Articles, then the Proceedings are to be founded on the Authority of the Church in a Convocation confirmed by the King. This is a Regular Method, and if Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> had took this way, he could have met with no ſort of obſtruction. But it is certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intolerable that a Book writ by a Biſhop, and Licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by an Archbiſhop, ſhould be thus attack'd, and a Biſhop be ſo openly defam'd.</p>
               <p>I have one thing more to add, and that is an account
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:95617:20"/> of that <hi>private Practice</hi> which our Author in his Preface objects againſt the Biſhop as unjuſt, and that is only this: When his Lordſhip came to the <hi>See</hi> of <hi>Sarum,</hi> he found the Prebends ſo ſcatter'd up and down <hi>England,</hi> that there was ſeldom a Surplice-man to Preach. The Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dral was often very ill ſerved. So he reſolved to keep the Dignities of the Church of <hi>Sarum</hi> within the Dioceſs, and to oblige thoſe that left the Dioceſs to leave the Church likewiſe, according to the <hi>Tenth Canon of the Council of Chalcedon.</hi> Which is this, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.<note place="margin">Beverig. Pandect. Canon. Tom. 1. p. 123.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Non liceat Clerico in duarum Civitatum Eccleſiis eodem tempore in Catalogum referri: Et in ea qua a principio ordinatus eſt, &amp; in ea in quam tanquam ad majorem confugit, propter inanis gloriae cupiditatem. Eos autem qui hoc faciunt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priae Eccleſiae reſtitui, in qua ab initio ordinati ſunt, ut illic ſolum miniſtrent. Sed ſi jam quiſpiam ex alia in aliam Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam tranſlatus eſt, nihil prioris Eccleſiae, vel corum quae ſub ea ſunt Martyriorum vel Phochotrophiorum vel Xenodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiorum rebus communicare.</hi> And elſewhere as well as in the <hi>Scholia</hi> upon this Canon they are very expreſs to the ſame purpoſe, That no Biſhop ſhall receive a Clergyman of another Dioceſs into his Church, under pain of Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication to both. In order to effect this, his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip was adviſed by an Ancient and Venerable Prelate, I may add, one of the Worthieſt and Learnedeſt now in the World, to take Bonds of Reſignation of thoſe to whom he gave Prebends, in caſe they ſhould go out of the Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs. There is no General Bond, this Condition is named and no other. This was alſo the more neceſſary, becauſe his Lordſhip hath hitherto generally given the Prebends to the Miniſters in Market-Towns, where the Labour is great, and the Proviſion mean. So unhandſomely does this Man reproach his Lordſhip, for a Method that ſeems ſo good and uſeful to the Church, and which could be compaſſed no other way but that which his Lordſhip made uſe of.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:95617:20"/>
               <head>Poſtſcript to the Stationer.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>SInce I ſent you theſe Papers, I underſtand by one, on whoſe Judgment I can well depend, that there is another Anſwer prepared by a very learned Hand; who has follow'd Mr. <hi>Hill,</hi> through all his Pretences to Learning and the Study of the Fathers; and diſcovers that he has juſt as much Knowledge as he has Modeſty, or good Breeding: Ignorance and ill Nature go often toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: For you know whoſe Character it is, <hi>That he ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth and is Confident.</hi> I ſhould be ſorry to have ſent this to you, when there is another ſo much perfecter coming to your Hand. But my Friend comforts me a little, by telling me, we write in ſuch different ways, that both ma prove acceptable, and make one Compleat Anſwer.</p>
               <p>I confeſs, I was amaz'd to hear there was ſo much Learning employed to refute ſo poor a Book; but the Anſwer made me was, that though Mr. <hi>Hill</hi>'s Book did not deſerve it, yet the Biſhop's did, and the Cauſe did it much more. It ſeemed neceſſary to take the Diverſion that Mr. <hi>Hill</hi>'s Book has perhaps given to Libertines and Atheiſts, (as well as to Socinians, and other ill-natur'd Men) out of the way, and to ſhew the World that Mr. <hi>Hill</hi> was all through, equally blinded with Ignorance and Malice. There is no hopes that any thing can convince ſo aukward a Man, as he ſeems to be. A ſhort piece of <hi>Parchment,</hi> founded on a <hi>Certain Statute,</hi> is perhaps, the only Anſwer that can work on him: Unleſs his Friends can prevent it, by ſhewing he has a better right to a Lodging in <hi>Moor-Fields,</hi> where good Air and Diſcipline may reſtore him to himſelf. This may ſeem too pleaſant; but it is really the charitableſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Thought that can be entertained of him: For I am ſure if his Head is ſound, his Heart is naught. Such Men as he, are born to be the Peſts of their
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:95617:21"/> Neighbourhood, and the Plagues of the Church; but I hope he will be ſo ſubdued, that the World ſhall be no more troubled with him.</p>
               <p>Only I will conclude with one pleaſant thing concerning him, which I have from ſo ſure a hand, that you may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon it, and publiſh it: While he was contriving to midwife this Book into the World, he apprehended, it ſeems, that it might raiſe a Storm; and he hoped to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure himſelf againſt that, by writing <hi>another Book</hi> in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the <hi>preſent Government,</hi> and for juſtifying the filling the <hi>Sees</hi> of the <hi>deprived Biſhops</hi> (as he had writ ſome Years ago, a Pamphlet, intituled <hi>Solomon</hi> and <hi>Abia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thar,</hi> upon the ſame ſubject) In <hi>this,</hi> he attack'd Mr. <hi>Dod—ll</hi>'s Principle with great Fury: This Book he ſent up to a Biſhop; and it ſeems he thought it was ſuch a Performance, and that the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> and the reſt of the Biſhops would have been ſo ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of this Service, (which to be ſure he thought a ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal one) that they muſt have abandoned the Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi> to the indignation of ſuch a Champion. But when he ſaw that ſmall account was had of that Trifle of his, (for without ſeeing it, I can eaſily believe nothing ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger can come from ſuch a Pen) and that the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop thought ſo baſe a Libel as this, was ſuch an Injury to the Church, as well as to the Order of Biſhops, that he required him to come and make all due Submiſſions and Reparation, otherwiſe he judged the Biſhop of <hi>Salis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> ought for the Churches ſake, as well as for his own, to proſecute him; he then reſolved to court his old Friends the <hi>Jacobites;</hi> (though, I am told, he treats them in that Book with the ſame brutality of Style, which he beſtows in this on the Biſhop.) And therefore he has very earneſtly deſired his Book may not be printed, but be ſent back to him again: and then if he had it once in his Hands, he would perhaps as impudently deny that ever he wrote any ſuch Book, as he begins now to deny that he is the Author of this; though if the Biſhop wants Proofs of it, this place can afford him a great many.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:95617:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
